# Zaheen Farraz Ahmad

CONTACT

CSC 2-11

Information

Department of Computing Science

University of Alberta Edmonton, AB, T6G 2E8 Email: zfahmad@ualberta.ca

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research interests mainly include areas in artificial intelligence with a focus on machine learning, search and optimization. Specifically, my work deals with aligning search and learning algorithms to work better together.

**EDUCATION** 

### University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada

Ph.D., Computing Science, Present

• Advisors: Michael Bowling, Levi Lelis

### University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada

M.Sc., Computing Science, 2017

- Thesis Topic: "Action Selection for Hammer Shots in Curling: Optimization of Non-convex Continuous Actions With Stochastic Action Outcomes"
- Advisor: Robert C. Holte

### Islamic University of Technology, Gazipur, Dhaka, Bangladesh

B.Sc., Computer Science and Engineering, 2012

- Thesis Topic: "Communication Requirement for Safety Applications in Low-Visibility for VANETs"
- Advisor: Md. Mahbub Alam

Honors and Awards

### Graduate Student Teaching Award, 2018

Award for outstanding teaching performance as a Graduate student

### IUT Gold Medal Award, 2012

Award for graduating with the highest GPA in the department at the Islamic University of Alberta (1 out of 50.)

#### SCHOLARSHIPS

# IUT Scholarship, 2008

Scholarship for covering 3 years of academic tuition at the Islamic University of Technology.

### ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

#### University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada

Graduate Research Assistant Fellow

May, 2014 - Present

- Conducting current Ph.D. research
- Main member of the Computer Curling Research Group
- Maintain the curling simulator software repository
- Supervised Undergraduate interns during their work in the summer semesters

### Teaching Assistant

Sep, 2013 - Dec, 2020

• Instructed and graded labs per semester for the introductory Computing Science courses targeted toward both CS and non-CS students

- Conducted supplementary lectures that provided extra coverage of difficult concepts in the course curriculum
- Instructed main lectures of the course when the professor was unavailable

### Islamic University of Technology, Gazipur, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Junior Lecturer

Dec, 2012 - Jul, 2013

 Helped design and instructed courses on Data Structures, Numerical Methods and Database Management Systems

# Professional Experience

#### AB Sciex Pte. Ltd.

Data Science Consultant

Dec, 2017 - Feb, 2018

2015

- Performed data analytics and machine learning evaluations
- Tested feasibility of automating microbacterial classification using artificial intelligence models

# ACADEMIC SERVICES

### Conference Reviewing

NeurIPS (2022), AAAI (2022)

### University of Alberta

Vice-President, Computing Science Graduate Student Association

### Islamic University of Technology

Treasurer, IUT Computing Society	2012
Organizing Member, National ICT Fest	2012

#### OUTREACH

### University of Alberta

Presenter, Iverson Day demos for high school students 2014 - 2019 Panelist, WP Wagner Panel on further education for high school students. 2015

#### Publications

#### Refereed Journals

[1] Durksen, T.L., Chu, Man-Wai., **Ahmad, Z.F.**, Radil, A.I., Daniels, L.M., "Motivation in a MOOC: a probabilistic analysis of online learners' basic psychological needs", *Social Psychology of Education*, pp.1-10. 2016

#### Refereed Conferences

- [1] Sokota, S., Ho, C., **Ahmad, Z.F.**, Kolter, J.Z., "Monte Carlo Tree Search With Iteratively Refining State Abstractions", *NeurIPS 2021*.
- [2] **Ahmad, Z.F.**, Lelis, L.H.S., Bowling, M., "Marginal Utility for Planning in Continuous and Large Discrete Action Spaces", *NeurIPS 2020*
- [3] **Ahmad, Z.F.**, Holte, R., Bowling, M., "Action Selection for Hammer Shots in Curling", *IJCAI 2016*.

#### Other Publications

[1] **Ahmad, Z.F.**, "Action Selection for Hammer Shots in Curling: Optimization of Non-convex Continuous Actions With Stochastic Action Outcomes" *M.Sc. Thesis, Department of Computing Science, Islamic University of Alberta.* 2017

- [2] Durksen, T.L., Chu, Man-Wai., **Ahmad, Z.F.**, Radil, A.I., Daniels, L.M., "Probabilistic analysis of academic engagement: Exploring student motivation through a massive open online course" (Abstract only), *Australian Association for Research in Education and New Zealand Association for Research in Education.* 2014
- [3] Ahmad, Z.F., Hossain, M.Md., "Communication Requirements for Safety Applications in Low Visibility for VANETs" B.Sc. Thesis, Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Islamic University of Technology. 2012